Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we have an upper intermediate level lesson for all of
我是Catherine，今天我们为大家准备了一节中高级课程，
you.
适合你们所有人。
That's right.
没错。
We're going to be talking business on this occasion on EnglishPod but specifically about
这次在EnglishPod上我们要谈商业，但具体是关于
planning a business.
规划一个企业。
Right.
对。
So before a business opens, a lot of planning has to happen.
所以在企业开业之前，需要做很多规划。
That means people will decide what kind of a product they want to sell, what kind of
这意味着人们要决定他们想卖什么产品、想进入什么样的市场等等。
a market they want to sell to, etc.
等等。
So that is the focus of today's lesson.
这就是今天课程的重点。
Let's take a listen to the dialogue for the first time and we'll be back in a minute to
让我们第一次听一下对话，稍后我们会回来
talk about what's going on.
讨论发生了什么。
I've had it.
我受够了。
I'm done working for a company that is taking me nowhere.
我不想再为一家让我毫无前途的公司工作了。
So what are you going to do?
那你打算怎么办？
Just quit?
直接辞职吗？
That's exactly what I'm going to do.
这正是我要做的。
I've decided to create my own company.
我决定创建自己的公司。
I'm going to write up a business plan, get some investors and start working for myself.
我要写一份商业计划书，找一些投资者，然后为自己工作。
Have you ever written up a business plan before?
你以前写过商业计划书吗？
Well, no.
嗯，没有。
It can't be that hard.
应该没那么难吧。
I mean, all you have to do is explain your business.
我的意思是，你只需要解释你的业务。
How are you going to do things?
你打算怎么做？
And that's it, right?
就这样，对吧？
You couldn't be more wrong.
你大错特错了。
A well-written business plan will include an executive summary which highlights the
一份写得好的商业计划书会包括一份执行摘要，用两页或更少的篇幅突出
idea of the business in two pages or less.
企业的核心理念。
Then you need to describe your company with information such as what type of legal structure
然后你需要描述你的公司，包括它是什么法律结构、历史等信息。
it has, history, etc.
等等。
Well that seems easy enough.
嗯，那看起来挺简单的。
Wait, there's more!
等等，还有更多！
Then you need to introduce and describe your goods or services, what they are and how they're
然后你需要介绍和描述你的商品或服务，它们是什么，以及它们如何
different from competitors.
与竞争对手不同。
Then comes the hard part, a market analysis.
接下来是难点：市场分析。
You need to investigate and analyse hundreds of variables.
你需要调查和分析数百个变量。
You need to take into consideration socio-economic factors from GDP per capita to how many children
你需要考虑社会经济因素，从人均GDP到人口平均
on average the population has.
有多少孩子。
All this information is useful so that you can move on to your strategy and implementation
所有这些信息都很有用，这样你就可以进入战略和实施阶段，
stage where you will describe in detail how you will actually execute your idea.
在那里你会详细描述你实际上如何执行你的想法。
Geez, is that all?
天哪，就这些吗？
Almost.
差不多。
The most important piece of information for your investors will be the financial analysis.
对投资者来说，最重要的信息是财务分析。
Here you will calculate and estimate sales, cash flow and profits.
在这里，你会计算和估算销售额、现金流和利润。
After all, people will want to know when they will begin to see a return on their investment.
毕竟，人们想知道他们什么时候能开始看到投资回报。
I think I'll just stick to my old job and save myself all the hassle of trying to start
我想我还是继续干我的老本行吧，省去创业的所有麻烦。
up a business.
创业。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So the guy wanted to open up a business but his friend explained that it's not so easy
所以那个家伙想开一家公司，但他的朋友解释说这没那么容易，
and gave a lot of interesting words and phrases there.
并给出了很多有趣的单词和短语。
He did.
确实如此。
He seemed a little naive.
他看起来有点天真。
Like he didn't really know how much work is involved in opening a business.
好像他不太了解开公司需要多少工作。
Exactly.
没错。
So I think we should take a look at some of the words used on Language Takeaway.
所以我认为我们应该看看“语言小贴士”部分用到的一些单词。
Language Takeaway
语言小贴士
The first word is the heart and soul of the process before you open a business.
第一个词是开公司前整个过程的核心和灵魂。
It's the business plan.
那就是商业计划书。
Alright so the business plan.
好的，商业计划书。
As you said it's a noun and it's basically a document that explains what's going on in
正如你所说，它是一个名词，基本上是一份解释公司状况的文件。
the business.
公司状况。
Exactly.
没错。
It's a paper that you write about the business that you want to open and it's a plan.
这是一份关于你想开的公司的书面文件，它是一个计划。
So that's what the name says.
所以名字就是这么来的。
You have to tell what you will do, how much money you will spend, how much money you will
你必须说明你要做什么、花多少钱、需要多少钱。
need.
需要多少钱。
Because if you're asking people for money, they want to know where the money will be
因为如果你向别人要钱，他们想知道钱会花在哪里，
spent if it's going to be spent on wise decisions.
是否花在明智的决策上。
Exactly.
没错。
And as you mentioned, you show this business plan maybe to a bank but also maybe to an
而且正如你提到的，你可能会把这份商业计划书展示给银行，也可能展示给
investor.
投资者。
That's right.
没错。
So investor is our next word.
所以投资者是我们的下一个词。
It's another noun but this noun is a person.
它也是一个名词，但这个名词指的是人。
A person is an investor.
一个人就是投资者。
If he or she gives money to someone else and expects more money to come back.
如果他或她把钱给别人，并期望更多的钱回来。
Right.
对。
So a person that's starting out a business maybe has enough money himself to open up
所以一个刚开始创业的人可能自己有足够的钱来开公司。
a business but sometimes you need extra money so you look for investors.
做生意有时候需要额外资金，所以你会寻找投资者。
People who are interested in giving you money.
就是那些愿意给你钱的人。
For example, I have a cupcake company.
比如，我有一家纸杯蛋糕公司。
I want to sell cupcakes to people and I need a thousand dollars.
我想把纸杯蛋糕卖给人们，需要一千美元。
So Marco, do you want to be an investor?
那么马可，你想当投资者吗？
Do you want to invest some money?
你想投资一些钱吗？
Yes.
是的。
For sure.
当然。
A cupcake company.
一家纸杯蛋糕公司。
That sounds great.
听起来不错。
I know but what happens if I don't sell cupcakes?
我知道，但如果我卖不出纸杯蛋糕呢？
That's a problem for you because you have made a risky investment.
那你就麻烦了，因为你做了高风险投资。
That's right.
没错。
So that's what happens with investors.
这就是投资者的情况。
But now if you want to attract the attention of your investors with your business plan,
但现在如果你想用商业计划吸引投资者的注意，
I think part of the most important aspects of this plan is the executive summary.
我认为这个计划最重要的部分之一是执行摘要。
A summary is usually an outline of the important points of a paper or a document.
摘要通常是论文或文件重要要点的概述。
So in this case I could say, Catherine's cupcake company will sell delicious cupcakes of 10
所以在这种情况下，我可以说，凯瑟琳的纸杯蛋糕公司将向5岁到55岁的市场销售10种不同口味的纸杯蛋糕。
different flavors to the market of 5 year olds, 55 year olds.
不同口味的纸杯蛋糕给5岁到55岁的市场。
People will love them.
人们会喜欢它们的。
She has a great secret recipe and she plans to triple her investments by next year.
她有一个绝密的配方，并计划明年将投资翻三倍。
Right.
对。
That's exactly it.
就是这样。
So if an investor reads the executive summary, which shouldn't be more than two pages long,
所以如果投资者阅读执行摘要，它不应该超过两页，
you can pretty much get the idea of what the business is about.
你基本上就能了解这个业务是关于什么的。
So if you want more details, you have to read the rest of the business plan.
所以如果你想要更多细节，就得读商业计划的其余部分。
But mainly with the executive summary, you can more or less know what it's all about.
但主要靠执行摘要，你大致就能知道它讲的是什么。
Exactly.
没错。
So a summary, like I said, is something that should be short and it should give you all
所以摘要，就像我说的，应该简短，并且要给你所有关于某事的最重要信息。
of the most important information about something.
没错。
Exactly.
And while they were talking more in depth about analyzing things and doing some research,
当他们更深入地讨论分析事物和做研究时，
and among those things, the girl mentioned the socio-economic factors.
在这些事情中，女孩提到了社会经济因素。
Okay, when I said we're going to sell cupcakes from my company to people between the ages
好的，当我说我们要把公司的纸杯蛋糕卖给5岁到55岁的人时，
of 5 and 55, we need to analyze, we need to look at their socio-economic factors.
我们需要分析，需要看他们的社会经济因素。
Socio comes from the word social.
“社会”来自“社会的”这个词。
It means where in society they are, they're upper class, middle class or lower class.
意思是他们在社会中的位置，是上层阶级、中产阶级还是下层阶级。
Economic means how much money do they make?
“经济”意味着他们赚多少钱？
Do they make $10,000 a year or $100,000 a year?
他们一年赚一万美元还是十万美元？
And so the kind of people we want to sell my cupcakes to will change according to their
所以我们想卖纸杯蛋糕给哪种人，会根据他们的社会经济因素而变化。
socio-economic factors.
社会经济因素。
That's right.
没错。
So as you mentioned, socio comes from the word social or from society.
所以正如你提到的，“社会”来自“社会的”或“社会”这个词。
So you're analyzing these factors from society.
所以你在分析来自社会的这些因素。
And well, part of these factors is the GDP per capita.
嗯，这些因素的一部分是人均GDP。
So we have two different words there.
所以我们有两个不同的词。
An acronym, GDP.
一个缩写词，GDP。
GDP, gross domestic product.
GDP，国内生产总值。
That might seem confusing because gross means different things at different times.
这可能看起来令人困惑，因为“gross”在不同时候意思不同。
But in this case, domestic means our country.
但在这里，“domestic”意思是我们的国家。
So within a country, all of the products added up together.
所以在一个国家内，所有产品加起来的总和。
Right.
对。
And gross is basically that.
“Gross”基本上就是这个意思。
Just all the products added up together without taking into consideration any other things.
就是把所有产品加起来，不考虑其他任何东西。
So the GDP is basically all the goods and services produced in a country within a given
所以GDP基本上是一个国家在给定时间内生产的所有商品和服务的总和。
time.
时间。
And what about per capita though?
那“per capita”呢？
So per capita comes from Latin.
“Per capita”来自拉丁语。
Per means four or each.
“Per”意思是“每”或“每个”。
And capita is a head.
“Capita”是“头”。
So this is per person.
所以这是“每人”。
So GDP per capita means how much, how many goods and services are made divided by the
所以人均GDP意味着生产了多少商品和服务，除以那个地方的人口数量。
number of people in that place.
人口数量。
Exactly.
没错。
So you probably have these indicators in your country or your own language as well.
所以你可能在你的国家或你自己的语言中也有这些指标。
But that's basically it.
但基本上就是这样。
And the acronym is gross domestic product.
这个缩写词是“国内生产总值”。
And just to explain a little bit, if you see this in Wikipedia or in an encyclopedia,
为了稍微解释一下，如果你在维基百科或百科全书中看到这个，
normally a very low GDP per capita is $500, American dollars.
通常很低的人均GDP是500美元，美元。
And a high one would be $35,000.
高的会是35,000美元。
$35,000, yeah.
35,000美元，是的。
And that's usually per year, right?
那通常是每年，对吧？
Because that's usually how it's taken into consideration.
因为通常是这样考虑的。
The time is a year.
时间是一年。
All right.
好的。
So those are the words that we have for you on language takeaway.
这些就是我们在“语言小贴士”中为你准备的词汇。
Now why don't we move on to a couple of different phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在我们为什么不转到“流利度构建器”中的几个不同短语呢？
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
Okay.
好的。
So this is important.
所以这很重要。
First phrase, Marco, has to do with our last first phrase.
第一个短语，Marco，和我们上一个第一个短语有关。
We had a business plan.
我们之前有一个商业计划。
So what do you do?
那你做什么呢？
You write up a business plan.
你起草一份商业计划。
Right.
对。
And that's a common way of saying to write or to create, to work on a business plan,
这是一种常见的说法，意思是写或创建、制定商业计划。
to write up.
起草。
Right.
对。
So it's something that we say that's very colloquial.
所以这是一个非常口语化的说法。
Something that is very spoken.
一种很口语化的表达。
And I can't explain why we say it, but you'll sound very fluent if you say, I'm going to
我解释不了为什么这么说，但如果你说“我要起草一份商业计划”，听起来会很流利。
write up a business plan.
起草一份商业计划。
Or why don't you write up a business plan?
或者“你为什么不起草一份商业计划呢？”
Right.
对。
So it would be correct to say, I'm going to write a business plan or I have to write a
所以正确说法是“我要写一份商业计划”或“我必须写一份商业计划”。
business plan.
商业计划。
But if you use this phrase, I'm going to write up a business plan, it's more fluent, right?
但如果你用这个短语“我要起草一份商业计划”，会更流利，对吧？
It's just more native-like.
更像母语者说的。
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好的。
And our next phrase is a return on investment.
我们的下一个短语是“投资回报”。
Okay.
好的。
So early we talked about investors.
之前我们谈到了投资者。
The money that they invest is called an investment.
他们投入的钱叫做投资。
Okay.
好的。
These words are all very closely related.
这些词都密切相关。
And when Marco decided to give money to my cupcake business, he expects the money to
当Marco决定给我的纸杯蛋糕生意投钱时，他期望钱能回来，而且实际上期望比投入的更多。
come back and he expects more actually to come back than what he put in.
回来。
So that's called a return on investment.
这就叫投资回报。
The money that's the difference.
差额部分就是回报。
So if he gives me a thousand dollars and I give him back $1,500 in a year, he made $500.
所以如果他给我一千美元，一年后我还他1500美元，他就赚了500美元。
That's amazing.
太棒了。
So that means it's a good return on his investment.
这意味着他的投资回报不错。
Right.
对。
So that's the term that we use, a return on investment.
这就是我们用的术语，投资回报。
So you don't say to return on investment, you see a return on investment.
所以你不说“去投资回报”，而是说“看到投资回报”。
Exactly.
没错。
It's a thing, it's a number, it's a quantity.
它是一个东西，一个数字，一个数量。
It's something you can count.
它是可以计量的。
Right.
对。
And well, in the end, after seeing that this business plan is not so easy, the guy said,
最后，在发现这个商业计划没那么简单之后，那个人说：“你知道吗？”
you know what?
你知道吗？
I'm not going to quit my job and just save myself the hassle.
我不打算辞职了，省得给自己找麻烦。
What's a hassle?
什么是“麻烦”？
The hassle.
麻烦。
That's an interesting word.
这是个有趣的词。
So if I'm going to save myself the hassle, a hassle is like the problem or the hard work
所以如果我说“省得给自己找麻烦”，麻烦就是指问题或涉及到的辛苦工作。
that it involves.
它涉及到的。
It's a lot of trouble.
就是很多麻烦。
A lot of trouble.
很多麻烦。
So I was going to cook some dinner tonight, but I'm going to save myself the hassle of
所以我今晚本来要做晚饭，但我要省去去杂货店买食材和做饭的麻烦，直接点外卖。
going to the grocery store and buying it and cooking it by just ordering food.
点外卖。
Right.
对。
So that's a good example.
这是个好例子。
Instead of doing all the work of cooking, you just save yourself the hassle, pick up
与其做所有做饭的工作，你不如省去麻烦，拿起电话让食物送到家。
the phone and get food delivered to your house.
送到你家。
Right.
对。
So you can change here, you can say save myself, save yourself, save his self.
所以这里可以变化，你可以说“省得我自己麻烦”、“省得你自己麻烦”、“省得他自己麻烦”。
So you change that pronoun.
所以你要改变那个代词。
The pronoun.
代词。
Exactly.
没错。
So you can save yourself the hassle or I'm just going to save myself the hassle.
所以你可以说“省得你自己麻烦”或“我就省得自己麻烦了”。
Okay.
好的。
So that's about it for fluency builder.
流利度训练就到这里。
Let's listen to today's dialogue one more time and we'll be back in a minute to talk
让我们再听一遍今天的对话，一会儿回来继续谈商业。
about business.
谈商业。
I've had it.
我受够了。
I'm done working for a company that is taking me nowhere.
我受够了为一家没有前途的公司工作。
So what are you going to do?
那你打算怎么办？
Just quit?
直接辞职？
That's exactly what I'm going to do.
我正是这么打算的。
I've decided to create my own company.
我决定创建自己的公司。
I'm going to write up a business plan, get some investors and start working for myself.
我要起草一份商业计划，找一些投资者，然后开始为自己工作。
Have you ever written up a business plan before?
你以前起草过商业计划吗？
Well, no, it can't be that hard.
嗯，没有，应该没那么难吧。
I mean, all you have to do is explain your business.
我的意思是，你只需要解释你的业务。
How are you going to do things?
你打算怎么做？
And that's it, right?
就这样，对吧？
You couldn't be more wrong.
你大错特错了。
A well-written business plan will include an executive summary, which highlights the
一份写得好的商业计划会包括一个执行摘要，它突出了
idea of the business in two pages or less.
用两页或更少的篇幅描述商业构想。
Then you need to describe your company with information such as what type of legal structure
然后你需要描述你的公司，包括法律结构类型等信息。
it has, history, etc.
它的历史等等。
Well, that seems easy enough.
嗯，这听起来挺简单的。
Wait, there's more.
等等，还有更多内容。
Then you need to introduce and describe your goods or services, what they are and how they're
然后你需要介绍和描述你的商品或服务，它们是什么以及如何
different from competitors.
与竞争对手不同。
Then comes the hard part, a market analysis.
接下来是难点：市场分析。
You need to investigate and analyze hundreds of variables.
你需要调查和分析数百个变量。
You need to take into consideration socioeconomic factors from GDP per capita to how many children
你需要考虑社会经济因素，从人均GDP到平均每个家庭有多少孩子。
on average the population has.
平均每个家庭有多少孩子。
All this information is useful so that you can move on to your strategy and implementation
所有这些信息都很有用，这样你就可以进入战略和实施
stage, where you will describe in detail how you will actually execute your idea.
阶段，在这里你将详细描述如何实际执行你的想法。
Geez, is that all?
天哪，就这些吗？
Almost.
差不多。
The most important piece of information for your investors will be the financial analysis.
对投资者来说，最重要的信息将是财务分析。
Here you will calculate and estimate sales, cash flow and profits.
在这里，你将计算和估算销售额、现金流和利润。
After all, people will want to know when they will begin to see a return on their investment.
毕竟，人们会想知道他们何时能开始看到投资回报。
I think I'll just stick to my old job and save myself all the hassle of trying to start
我想我还是继续干我的老本行吧，省去创业的麻烦。
up a business.
创业的麻烦。
So it was pretty interesting that he wanted to quit his job and just, you know, set up
所以，他想辞职然后创业这件事挺有意思的。
a business.
创业。
But actually, many people say that business plans are unnecessary.
但实际上，很多人说商业计划书是不必要的。
Really?
真的吗？
Do these people have lots of money and they don't need investors?
这些人是不是很有钱，不需要投资者？
I think the problem is that there are many books out there that give you clear examples
我认为问题在于有很多书给出了明确的例子，
of companies, Fortune 500 companies, that started out without a business plan.
比如《财富》500强公司，它们一开始并没有商业计划书。
So I think many people take this as a rule.
所以我认为很多人把这当成了一条规则。
A rule.
一条规则。
Like, well, they didn't need one or it's not really necessary or why should I write up
比如，他们不需要商业计划书，或者它真的不是必需的，或者我为什么要写
a business plan?
一份商业计划书？
Well, I'm not an entrepreneur and I'm not a business person, but my feeling is that
嗯，我不是企业家，也不是商人，但我的感觉是
a business plan is as much for investors as it is for yourself.
商业计划书既是为投资者准备的，也是为你自己准备的。
It helps you clarify your goals.
它帮助你明确目标。
It helps you explain your objectives to your future colleagues.
它帮助你向未来的同事解释你的目标。
And I think it's just a really good way to map out the first year of a business because
而且我认为这是规划企业第一年的好方法，因为
it tends to, a lot of businesses fail in that first year.
很多企业往往在第一年就失败了。
So I think this is a really important step.
所以我认为这是非常重要的一步。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，没错。
So it's very interesting.
所以这非常有趣。
We've talked a little bit about business here, but we would like to know your ideas or your
我们在这里稍微讨论了一下商业，但我们想知道你的想法或
comments or any other suggestions that you have about this topic or any topic on EnglishPod.
评论，或者你对这个话题或EnglishPod上任何话题的其他建议。
So why don't you send us a comment or a personal message.
所以，为什么不给我们发一条评论或一条私人消息呢。
We are at EnglishPod.com and we'll see you guys there.
我们在EnglishPod.com，我们会在那里见你们。
Bye everyone.
大家再见。
See you there.
那里见。